Wouldn't it be a shame if all those
health
influencers that talked about Torine's
health benefits suddenly had to walk
those statements back? That happens
sometimes, or it should happen if a
person is ethical. But is that what
should happen here? A big new study
released just a few weeks ago indicating
that torine is not only linked to cancer
but accelerates cancer directly. Since
torine, an amino acid produced by our
body, but also discovered to offer
multiple health benefits when consumed,
has been making some waves for its
possible longevity benefits, its
cardiovascular benefits, its exercise
benefits, and more. It might be
surprising to suddenly see it attached
to cancer. This uh study looks primarily
at animal data but does also introduce
human data that we'll get to. First, the
researchers identified torine as being
heavily implicated in multiple leukemas.
These are blood cancers, especially
immune cell cancers that originate in
your bone marrow where your immune cells
among other cells begin their life. The
researchers were initially interested in
the cancer micro environment, the
surrounding area that the cancer rests
in and around. This area is full of
support cells like fibroblasts,
endothelial cells, stem cells,
structural proteins and much more. This
micro environment releases different
molecules and interacts with nearby
cells to allow cancer cells to multiply
and leave known as metastasis. In fact,
if we look at the cycle of cancer
progression and map it against these
micro environment cells, we can see
changes in how these support cells
change over the cancer progression. On
the bottom we have four defined stages
of cancer and the vertical axis is the
proportional amount of these support
cells and the colored lines indicate the
amount of each type of support cell. As
one example we can see that these cancer
cells known as leukemic cells progress
into expansion or growth. The osteo1
lineage of cells bone cells dramatically
decrease and we see more MSC's meenyal
stem cells. The point here being that
the tumor cancer micro environment
changes to presumably support the
leukemic cancer cell development. Why am
I telling you all this? Well, the
researchers point out that while torine
is known to be produced by the liver
primarily, bone marrow cells also have
the ability to produce torine, implying
that torine is a key molecule in cancer
progression. In fact, they offer
evidence by injecting genetically
modified leukemic cells into mice and
identifying if the mice survive longer
if they're injected with leukemic cells
devoid of the torine transporter or with
the torine transporter. So to be clear,
both groups have cancer. One cancer is
missing the transporter that allows
torine into the cell, effectively
divorcing the regular cancer from the
impact torine might have. If we look at
that data, we have the survival data on
the vertical axis. higher is better and
the time that's elapsed on the
horizontal. The blue line is the cancer
with an intact torine transporter and
the green line is the cancer with the
torine transporter knocked out. As you
can see, all the mice with the torine
transporter included leukemia die. And
although the other mice, well, they're
not exactly celebrating their condition,
they do much better with some even
surviving altogether. This dams the
torine transporter and by extension
torine as a major determinant for
leukemia's deadliness. But how does it
do that? One of the primary ways that
your cells end their existence when
destabilizing into cancer is through a
mechanism called apoptosis as well as
necrosis. These are both ways for the
cell to die. Unfortunately, that goes
against the cancer agenda and we
wouldn't have cancer if these mechanisms
worked well all the time. So they
clearly have been compromised. Part of
those mechanisms is mediated by a family
of proteins called the BCL family.
They're a pretty tumultuous relationship
amongst themselves. But BCL2 is an
anti-apoptosis protein. It blocks cell
death by binding proapoptosis proteins
and sequestering them, disabling them
from killing the cell. Not what you want
in cancer. If we look at that data, you
can focus on the right graphs. The
higher the bars, the more cell death, a
good thing. The plus and negative at the
bottom is the presence and absence of
the torine transporter. Clearly, with
the torine transporter present, there's
less cell death. So, somehow torine or
the transporter is leading to reduced
sensitivity to cell death. There's even
further evidence of that that we'll get
into. We'll uh look into some of the
subtypes of leukemia as well as human
data and then get into how we should be
thinking about torine going forward.
Should you cut it out of your supplement
stack, for example? If you want more on
the mechanisms of torine, especially on
how it affects cancer metabolism,
torine's cancer growth effects, and some
more details on the study, check out my
premium research review. It's called the
Physiionic Insiders. you not only get
access to this full analysis of this
study, but hundreds of studies,
including 30-cond written summaries, uh,
exclusive videos and exclusive podcast,
live sessions with me, and more. The
links in the description box if you're
interested. We see torine's role further
evidenced when looking at different
subtypes of leukemia, those with
different genetic backgrounds like
primitive AML and monocyic AML. Monocyic
AML. So AML stands for acute myoid
leukemia FYI is known to be a more
drugresistant version of leukemia and we
can see it has far greater expression of
the torine transporter gene also known
as SLC 6A6 indicated on the vertical
axis. So the transporter is at least
associated with increased drug
resistance which probably doesn't
exactly bode well for survival. Now, all
this has been in mice. And as people
enjoy reminding each other, it's just a
mouse study. It means
nothing. We definitely shouldn't over
interpret these data on their own, but
the researchers do include some
translational evidence in humans. Here
we're looking at patients with leukemia.
And again, as morbid as it is, the
vertical axis indicates survival. So the
further up and to the right, the better.
The horizontal axis is time and the
11.14 marker is the cutoff for high and
low expression of the torine
transporter. Clearly, people the green
line that have greater expression of the
torine transporter have worse survival.
In addition, there's an important clue
in the right graph. We're looking at the
torine transporter expression in human
cells on the vertical axis. Higher is
more normal. There are non-cancerous
bone marrow cells. and the two types of
focus leukemia. So BCCML or blast crisis
chronic myoid leukemia and AML so acute
myoid leukemia. Clearly both leukemias
have far greater expression of the
torine transporter. So while we still
can't fully say everything that we see
in animals is true for humans, we
clearly see some strong similarities. In
the end, what does this mean for two
groups of people? one, people who
supplement with torine and two, people
with cancer. Well, while people have
reached out to me to ask about this
study because they're concerned about
their daily torine intake, notice how
none of the data discussed went over how
consuming torine actually creates
cancer. In fact, while there's clearly a
close relationship between torine and
its transporter into the cells, the
researchers didn't assess
supplementation of torine, but focused
on the tumor micro environment
potentially using torine to accelerate
cancer growth. It seems reasonable that
if this held true and a person
supplemented with exogenous torine,
they'd see similar effects, but we don't
know that for a fact. As a final note,
I'd add that if we look at this human
data, again, this sudden increase in the
torine transporter might also require a
bunch of genetic changes that are unique
to cancer. So, simply consuming torine,
even if it did increase torine
transporter number, may not actually do
anything because there isn't that
cancerous background. Either way, for
people without cancer, nothing in this
study tells us there is a risk. As for
people with cancer, we can only speak to
leukemias and even there this is
preliminary evidence, but it depends on
your risk tolerance since this study
still doesn't inform on actual
supplementation. Although the
researchers do warn that supplementation
of any sort may be something to avoid
for people with leukemia, even if torine
has been linked to positive outcomes in
other regards of health. So, if you want
more direct evidence, this study
shouldn't budge you. But if you're
wanting to be extra careful, it's not
unreasonable to cut down on torine
consumption, especially since torine is
a conditionally non-essential amino
acid. What's fascinating is that there's
this massive study on the longevity
effects of torine that released a few
years ago. I mean, what a stark
contrast. You can find it right here.
Thanks for hanging out.